Welcome
back to another video from ItsDrDan,
and this time we're going to be
doing an introduction to heat and
energy for introductory chemistry.
So for whenever we have come
across heat and energy problems,
these can be extremely confusing,
especially the first time you were
seeing them because they involve a
lot of simple algebraic equations.
So let's try to break it down
to see what you're going to be
seeing in these kinds of problems.
So the first thing is, is
you're going to be coming across
heating and cooling curves.
So a lot of times you're going to get
different types of diagrams that look
similar to the ones that I have here,
where there's going to be temperature
on one axis, energy on the other.
So if something is being heated,
what we generally see that as is
as a slope that is going upwards.
And if something is being cooled,
it is as a slope going downwards.
So these are the two things
that we're going to be seeing.
So we have cooling and heating.
So whenever this is happening, the whole
idea with slopes is that the way that we
can do mathematical calculations regarding
these is using the MCAT equation.
So it's q is equal to m c Delta T.
So anyone that's a pre med out there
who might want to be a doctor one day,
MCAT, it's a quick way to remember it.
So what is all that
really broken down into?
What does all these
different symbols mean?
So for this one, it's all about change.
So slope is all about change.
It's the same idea.
So whenever we have Q,
that represents heat.
And that's generally written in
the units of joules or calories.
Very similar to the calories
that we ingest every day.
We also have m for mass.
That is going to be shown in grams.
We have C, which C in this
case is for specific heat.
Now, specific heat is for a specific
substance, meaning that it is unique
for every single material that exists.
Okay, so specific heat.
So this is unique, so
I'll write that down.
So, when it comes to specific heat,
the big thing with that one is it
reveals the units that are going
to be used in the entire equation.
So this one is Joules,
grams, over Celsius.
And then when it comes to delta
T, well, all right, well, what
does that all break down to?
Well, if you ever see a delta
symbol, that's telling you that
you have a change in something.
And the way that that is calculated
is the final temperature.
So wherever your final cooling spot is,
wherever your, your, uh, end point is.
minus your initial starting temperature.
So if you're doing this in the lab, most
likely what you're going to be doing is
taking a thermometer, measuring something
at the very start of your experiment,
mixing some chemicals together, and then
you're going to see a temperature change.
So from there, what kind of,
what other things might we see?
So another type of representation
using these types of curves
is by showing plateaus.
So if I have this heating curve
again, and I just want to show it by
a flat line, so a plateau, this is
representing that you are going through
a phase change, or a phase transition.
So what that means is that this
is something that requires a lot
of energy, And all it's doing is
going from maybe from a solid to
a liquid or a liquid to a gas.
So, and those are represented
by very specific terminology.
So if I'm going from a solid
To a liquid or vice versa.
This is always in representation of
melting and freezing, but we're going
to be talking about things in a more
thermodynamic or heat sense meaning
that this is represented by Fusion
meaning we're bringing together or
bringing atoms closer together or slat
are starting to bring them apart So for
this one, it's also represented by heat
So this is a different version of Q.
So, I'm going to label
it as Q, but, or as heat.
And this is moles, so n for
moles, times delta H of fusion.
Okay, and this one's generally
in kilojoules, is what that
one's going to be represented by.
Now we also have when a liquid can
turn into a gas, so when that occurs,
this is when we're vaporizing something
or we're turning it into particles.
So when that's occurring, this is
gonna be another type of heat equation.
Very similar.
So it's Q heat and that's moles
times delta H of vaporization.
And this one's occurring whenever
we have something that's boiling
or going through condensation.
So if you were kind of in class recently
and your teacher is going over all kinds
of different parts of phase changes, this
is where we have to pay attention and
see where are the temperatures rising to
our, is it going to cross a phase change?
So what kind of problems
can we see with all this?
This is a lot of information
that we're going to kind of
start to see how we can apply it.
So we have how many
different equations here?
We have two major or
three different equations.
So let's kind of highlight
those for ourselves.
So we have the MCAT equation.
That is one of them.
Extremely important.
Definitely write it down.
Then you have your two, um, your two, uh,
different phase change equations, which
are similar, but they're going to require
different constants that are applied.
So Delta H is a constant
that will be given to you.
All right.
So I probably, I've made
a couple of questions.
So the first one here is how much
heat is absorbed when 10 grams
of water goes from 15 degrees C.
So, being that this type of problem talks
about a phase change, or sorry not a
phase change, a change in temperature,
apologies, that means that we are
going to be using the MCAT equation.
And that's because in this problem, you
can see that we're changing temperature.
So when we're doing this problem,
we want to write everything down.
So as we're kind of seeing,
going, looking at this problem,
we can see a couple of key things.
We see that, all right,
there's 10 grams of water.
That is also a good part of information.
This is water.
Meaning we need to see what its
specific value is for specific heat.
That's why I include the table to the left
and we have temperatures here as well.
So we need to make sure we clearly label
what each of these values represent.
So first thing is for MCAT
equation, we need mass.
Mass in this problem is 10 grams.
Now we have water.
So C.
It's gonna go off of this table
that I have on the left, and we can
see water down here at the bottom,
and what that says is that's 4.
184.
Now, those units are written on
the top of that column, so that's
joules over grams by Celsius.
Now, what else do we have?
We have Ti, so your initial starting
point, and that mentions it's going
to start at 15 grams, or sorry,
not 15 grams, 15 degrees Celsius.
And then we have final temperature.
which is 50 degrees Celsius.
The first thing we want to do
really quickly for ourselves to
help make our problem a little bit
easier is we can calculate what
our change in temperature is, which
is your final minus your initial.
So we'll take those two values.
So delta T is your final,
which is 50 degrees.
Minus your initial, which is
50 degrees C, and that's going
to equal 35 degrees Celsius.
Okay, now that is going to get
plugged into our MCAT equation.
So what that's going to be is that
Q is equal to 10 grams times the 4.
184 joules over grams by Celsius.
So when we do that, we're going to
take all those values, plug them in.
We're now going to put in our temperature,
which is 35 degrees C, and we're
going to multiply all these values.
So we take 10, Times 4.
184 times 35.
So, when you get that, you should get
the following value from your calculator.
You'll get 1, 464.
4 joules.
Now, is that a right
way to represent this?
If you remember from your beginning days
of chem, significant figures, right?
So that's always something that's
going to plague us for all eternity.
It's something we're always going
to see throughout chemistry.
So, in this problem, all your
starting values, you go off your
lowest one, in terms of sig figs,
and all of our starting ones are 3
and 4 sig figs, 3 being the lowest.
So, we're going to round
our answer to 1460 joules.
And that would be our
final answer for heat.
Now, what if I ask you to convert
the previous answer to calories?
So sometimes in these different problems,
you're going to be given, you're going
to be told to make it in calories, which
is because it's a more relatable unit to
the health sciences field, and which is
one of our biggest points of this channel
is trying to help health science majors.
So with that.
What we will do is we'll take our
original value before we rounded it off.
So that way we get the most
accurate representation of calories.
And then we'll round that
calorie value to 3 sig figs.
So, let's do it.
So how, what is the conversion
from calories to joules?
Well, it's actually a pretty easy one.
It's the same thing as a
specific heat of water.
A lot of our science is based on water.
So, with this one, it's 4.
184 joules is equal to 1 calorie.
And that's a lowercase c.
So, with that, we'll take the 464.
4 joules.
We'll write our t table.
And now we've got to
cancel out our units, so 4.
184 joules, we're going to show that
cancellation, if I can get this to
cooperate, joules will cancel joules,
they are opposite each other, and then
calories is on top, that's the only
thing that remains, so we take 1464.
4 divided by 4.
184 and we will get 350
calories as our answer.
So, now we know how to do two things,
we know how to do slopes for heating,
which was our previous problem,
and now we can convert to calories.
What other type of problems do you have?
A big one that you're kind of given
a lot when it comes to a lab based
course is you might be given an unknown
metal that you have to actually try
to figure out what is it made out of.
Now, being that every substance has
its own unique value to it, you can...
You can identify what it is.
You can figure out if it's brass
or silver, gold, lead, you name it.
The value exists in different tables
to figure out what it could be.
So, if I have a sample of an unknown
metal with a mass of 125 grams, and
it rises in temperature by 10 degrees
Celsius when 481 joules of heat is
added, What element is the metal?
So what we're trying to do is we're
trying to solve for C or specific heat.
So when we have this equation,
we're going to be using our MCAT
equation, but we're going to be
rearranging it to get C by itself.
So what's the easiest way to do that?
Well, if I divide both sides by m
and delta t, we'll have a couple
things that will cancel out.
m will cancel and then delta t
will cancel, leaving c by itself.
So what this equation is going to turn
into is c is equal to q m delta t.
So now we can plug in all of our values.
So our q, in this case,
Was the 481 joules.
We had a mass, which was 125 grams, and
then we had a delta T of 10 degrees C.
Now, when we plug all that in, so we
do 481, and we divide by 125 times 10
in parenthesis, and you should get 0.
385 joules over grams by Celsius, which
is your units of, of, of specific heat.
So now when we have that value,
now our, our big thing is, is try
to figure out what metal is it?
Well, how do I do that?
Well, hopefully you're given a table.
If not, you might need, you
need to look in your textbook.
There's usually tables at the end of them.
So, but for us, we have
a little table here.
So we had 0.
385.
So with that, you can see that, oh,
That matches the value of copper.
So our experiment showed that we have
copper as our unknown metal, which is
great, that's exactly what we want.
Now, what's the hardest
type of problem you can see?
Let's go through it.
So whenever you're given a problem,
sometimes you might have a type of problem
that goes through many different phase
changes and heating, meaning it's putting
it all together in one super problem.
So what does that mean?
What is it going to look like?
So here's an example.
If I ask you, how much heat in kilojoules?
is required to turn 100 grams
of ice at negative 100 degrees
C to steam at 250 degrees C.
Why the heck do you even calculate that?
So I give a bunch of C values for it.
Notice how the specific heat
changes from ice to water to steam.
So one huge tip for any heating,
cooling, phase change problem is you
want to go back through it And try
to diagram it out using slopes and
plateaus so that you can see what
calculations you need to complete.
Because for every slope,
meaning every point between a
transition, use the MCAT equation.
For every flat point, you're going
to be using either the fusion
or the vaporization formula.
So, let's map out R's.
So for this one, it says that we
start at negative 100 degrees C.
That's really cold.
So what we have to do is remember
what the freezing point and
the boiling point is of water.
So for us, I put down here
the the melting point here.
So the melting point for
water is 0 degrees C.
So our original temperature is
going to be starting somewhere
around 100, negative 100 degrees.
So it's really cold, so negative 100.
And what that's going to be
doing is it's going to be
heating up to its first plateau.
So we're just going to arbitrarily
label these, so we're going to say
this is 0 degrees right around here.
Now, at the first plateau, that
is going to be a flat spot.
So meaning that at our first slope
we're going to do one calculation, our
first plateau we're going to do a second
one, so we can kind of map these out.
That we had a slope first.
That is going to be an MCAT equation.
Our second one we're gonna be doing
using the, and we'll label these
Q one, Q two, just to kind of keep
ourselves, keep our brain straight.
We're gonna be using the heat of
fusion for that one, 'cause the
delta H for fusion was for melting.
Now, do, does our problem stop?
Well, it said we're going to
250 degrees, so from 0 to 100
is where the boiling point ends.
So what we're gonna have
another, another curve going up.
So, for that one, we're once
again gonna be heating, and that's
gonna be our third calculation.
So we'll have three, and that
one's gonna be identical,
very similar to the first one.
We're going to be doing
another MCAT equation.
Now keep in mind, we got to remember
what phase all these are in.
So the first one was ice, and we became a
liquid, so the third one is referring to
a liquid, and if the one that we get to
a fifth one, that's going to be as steam.
All right, so then we'll have another
plateau, which is now referring to
When we take our n value and times
that by our heat of vaporization,
then we will have one
more going all the way up.
So, this is 100 degrees C, and
then up here is 250 degrees C.
So that water is getting steaming hot.
So, when we take that, this
is all of our equations.
We're just mapping out what we need to do.
So, how do you find out the heat?
Well...
We just did it for five different things.
So you have to add them all up in the end.
So to find the total energy, what
we're going to be doing is adding
up one plus two plus three plus four
and five when you go through these.
So it's going to be a lot of calculations
and making sure your numbers are correct.
So let's try to do it together
and see if we can do it.
And like I mentioned, this
is a challenge problem.
It's something that takes a little longer
to do, so it can be extremely difficult.
So with that, let's start with number one.
So one was referring to ice.
So with the ice calculation, the big
thing with this one is that we had a
lot of different pieces of information.
We have that, um, we can kind of.
Write it all out here again for
ourselves before we get started.
The mass was 100 grams.
A lot of the, uh, the second and
third, or second and fourth part
of this calculation require moles.
So we could quickly try to calculate
the number of moles of this too.
So moles, how can we do that?
Well it's 100 grams of water.
So we need to convert it to moles.
The best way to do that
is to use molar mass.
So if we have 18 grams of water.
For every one mole, and that's
from your periodic table, these
are going to cancel, and that's
going to give us roughly about 5.
56 moles of water.
So we have that value for ourselves.
Um, let's see, and is there any
other values that were given
other than the temperatures?
So we have a lot of temperatures.
So, let's do number one.
So, one is taking our MCAT equation.
Which requires us to go through
writing, uh, taking our mass.
This is when it was ice, so we
gotta take our ice specific heat.
So ice was an orange, so that was 2.
04.
Joules per grams per Celsius,
and that's going from negative
100 degrees C to 0 degrees C.
So that's a change of, so we have
final minus initial, so that's a
hundred degrees Celsius of change that
this is going to be going through.
So when we take all those different parts,
we multiply them all together, we're going
to be getting over 20 1, 400 joules of
energy, which being that we're planning
on putting it on kilojoules, we can do
a quick little conversion for ourselves.
1, 000 joules, that's one
kilojoule, meaning that we have 20.
4 kilojoules, and that's for part one.
One now part two with this one.
This is our first phase change, but
we already did most of the work for it
So what we have to do is take our heat
value and we're gonna have moles times
our Delta H of Fusion so our moles
was five point five six moles Times
our Delta H of fusion which we grabbed
from our table and that's six point.
Oh two kilojoules
Okay, now when we multiply these
values, we're gonna get 33.
5 kilojoules for our first transition.
Our next part was heating it again,
so it's keeping it straight, so
now we're here on the curve, so
we're going from 0 degrees to 100
degrees, so we're doing it again.
So when we go through that, that heating
process again, We're going to take our
same MCAT equation, so we're going to
take 100 grams, times it by the value for
water, for C, which was in blue, was 4.
184 joules per grams by Celsius.
We're then going to be taking our Tf minus
Ti, which would be 100 minus 0, so it's
going to be once again 100 degrees C.
And that's going to give us a
value of 41, 840 joules, which
we can then convert to 41.
8 kilojoules.
Keep in mind, we're going to be
adding up all these in the end.
What a problem.
Alright, so, now, when we take this,
we got our last phase change, which
is, once again, taking the number
of moles times the vaporization.
So, we have 40.
7 as our constant for this.
We're going to times that by our moles.
So, Q4.
is our moles, so 5.
56 moles times the 40.
7 kilojoules per mole.
Notice how it takes way more energy
to, to turn something into a gas.
So when that happens, that's going
to be a value of 226 kilojoules.
Now the last part is going
to be one more MCAT equation.
Where now we're going from Tf being 250
degrees and our Ti is 100 degrees C.
So, let's plug it all in.
So our last one is we
had a 100 gram sample.
We're gonna plug it, we're
gonna times it by our C value.
Which, for steam, was 2.
times 150 degrees, which was
our difference, or our delta T.
So, when we go through
this, we have 100 times 2.
09 times 150, and then we have
our final calculation, which,
in this case, is going to be 31.
4 kilojoules.
Alright, so now what are we
going to do for our final total?
We're going to add up all
the circled information.
So for number one, so
what are we going to do?
We're going to take 1, plus
2, plus 3, plus 4, and plus 5.
So let's write all those out.
So we had 31.
4 kilojoules for 5, 226.
For 4, and this is really important to
make sure they're all the same units,
when we're adding these, we had 41.
8 kilojoules for 3, 33.
5 kilojoules for 2, and then we had 20.
4 for 1.
Alright, so when we add up all
these values together, we're going
to get a total final value of 353.
1 kilojoules for overall energy and heat.
This is the hardest type problem you
can have for this, where it's something
that involves many page, a lot of
calculations going through it, but it's
the same type of algebraic equation.
The most important part is staying
organized from the start, so that way
you can label your slopes, label your
plateaus, so you can map out your
equations when you're going through it.
And you're going to be using your
different values going through it.
So it's mainly using the MCAT
equation, which is the most
important one to know how to use.
The phase changes usually are not as
much, it's more important to focus
on how to use that MCAT equation.
So hopefully this video helped.
It was a little bit of a longer one,
but there was a lot of information
to talk about So please consider
to like and subscribe for future
videos, and I'll try to be help making
more content as we go All right.
Bye now